[SPEAKER_00]: So, in terms of not-self, a person can get the idea that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Most people have...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, a normal human being knows they are going to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they know, without reflecting that much, I'm not in control of my body fully, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they get that idea that it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, I'm not in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they don't... they don't understand not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: They still take things personally.
[SPEAKER_00]: They still take the body personally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though you know, overall, you're going to die.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: I was supposed to say, they haven't really thought about it deep enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or contemplated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... And...
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people did.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still being infatuated with life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of how they act.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they act as though it is theirs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can have all the ideas you want, but if your behavior is not mirroring those ideas, that's where you're fueling those wrong assumptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, on one end, yes, when you're, you know, thinking clearly, you recognize all these characteristics of existence,
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, out of habits and carelessness, the body still goes towards sensuality, resists discomfort, indulges in food, doesn't practice sense restraint, and that's the cesspit of the... that's the like the... the roots where your wrong views are being fed from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, although your ideas are, you know, different to that, you're actually going about things, it's very much accordance to sense of control and I'm gonna live forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, you need to have the right ideas, but now you need to start doing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to start doing the right... You need to start... like, you need to purify your behavior, as the Buddha said, to mirror those ideas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, and it's like... exactly, that's... and that's why there were summoners and brahmins outside of the Buddha's teaching, who did actually...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your sense of control.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can end at any moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said that's like the foremost of the outsider's views.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the point was that, now, if you actually, not just think that view once a month, or be convinced that you're holder of that view, but, okay, start, whenever you want to act towards the world, towards him, her, or this or that, you first put that view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you're nothing to no one anywhere in the world and nobody's nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's just, oh, you would not be able to engage in passion, aversion, distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there were then people who made the effort and their behavior did start to correspond to those views.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those were the people that Buddha met in the suttas who needed very little instruction for final liberation, because they did a great amount of work already.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for example, if...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I might logically or reason that feelings are not mine because they're always changing and, you know, what do I feel now?
[SPEAKER_00]: I feel pain now, I feel pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, yeah, I can see that now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, I can...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can even record all my feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ten o'clock was like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the time now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Collect information about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Study it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I can see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Definitely, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's it's kind of mirrors at right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, on paper.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In theory.
[SPEAKER_01]: But... Well, that's in the nutshell, Abhidhamma and commentaries, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that impersonal take, almost like a scientific collection of observational facts of the Buddhist teachings.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all this, like, the list and comparisons and permutations.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not the dhamma, because... Go on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I see that it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I understand in theory that it's impermanent, or inaccessible to my control, the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, as I feel, what do I do when I'm feeling pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I must...
[SPEAKER_00]: I must... Am I trying to get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or am I unmoved by it?
[SPEAKER_01]: I must graft that idea onto... Inevitably, you'll be trying to get rid of it through using those ideas, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you then really start to understand those ideas, you realize, yeah, thinking about the dhamma does not mean that's the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can have all the ideas, but if you're not actually applying it rightly, there is no dhamma there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's important to recognize because otherwise people can easily slip into a view of, well, as long as I think about the dhamma, I am on the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're on the path when you become a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the beginning of the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not if you don't see the dhamma means you don't see the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you be on the path if you don't see the path?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will not become a sotāpanna just on account of such ideas.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to actually start applying them and enduing things on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I say, well, feelings are not mine, not my personal things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Great.
[SPEAKER_00]: Theory.
[SPEAKER_01]: You got it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I'm feeling a lot of pain or prospect of pleasure, a lot of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's say there is a prospect of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, let me apply that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what do you do in the face of prospect of pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't delight in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, what else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you act towards it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Follow it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, so you endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: For how long?
[SPEAKER_00]: Forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if those are the truths that you understood, that you accepted, that you intellectually verified as correct, now you start doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this thing is not mine?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not in my control.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's saying... but... but I'm... say... say, in the beginning, I am faced with feeling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This feeling is pressuring me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's touching me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It does feel like mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I have the outside view of the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have an op...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have an option now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It feels like yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the option there is, okay, so what do you do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you accept the pressure that it's yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do you not accept it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, look, this is yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you know, when when the fisherman throws a bait with the food, it's for the fish.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that you get hooked.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I accept the pressure, the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You accept the pressure, you accept the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, sorry, I accept that there is pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is, that is a bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you might not necessarily see the bait, but you can already understand it by not acting out of pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are safe in regard to the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not see it immediately, but at least you know, as long as I don't take this, there will be no bait I'm hooked with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why I say it's important to recognize that dhamma begins with sotāpatti, not with the ideas of dhamma and even the clarity you might have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you do, you will be creating that discrepancy between your ideas that you're convinced are putting you on the path of dhamma, and your behavior that it's still not matching it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your lack of endurance, your lack of recognition at the right level, lack of restraint in regard to need to manage discomfort and unpleasant things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't have such view, and you recognize, yeah, these ideas, as clear and as pleasing as they are, they might be very right, and I might verify later on that I was spot-on right from the start, but the only way I'll do that...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about, you know, through holding these views about the ideas and so on, and feeling saved on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now let me do that in regard to sensuality, aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only three things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to seek the verification anywhere else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's how you... yeah, well, that's how you verify.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you can only... you will ever only be able to verify.
[SPEAKER_00]: So when things pressure you... Because I can have a view and you can agree with my view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can both agree that feelings are not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and we can write scholarly papers on it, and dissertations, and pages and pages of references, and create a whole network of information.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the information of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dhamma is when things are endured on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I understand feelings are not myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't belong to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, they just come and go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, when things come and go, let them come and go without acting out of them, without trying to get rid of them, without delighting them, without welcoming them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as it takes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it might take forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a way, the verification that has worked is the fact that feelings no longer pressure you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, eventually, yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just even the pressure felt will not be... well, it will diminish.
[SPEAKER_01]: There will be no pressure in the end.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, like, contact cannot... pāsa, the pressure, contact, whatever you translate it, cannot pressure the groundless one, when there is no ground to apply that pressure for an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he... arahant is unable,
[SPEAKER_01]: To experience pressure of any kind anymore, mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing can pressure him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's nothing for him anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that determination of self, that thing that determines self, is no longer there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but now we're getting a bit abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, you can speculate about it, but... No, because he endured things sufficiently on the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why nothing can pressure him anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the difference, as I said many times before.
[SPEAKER_01]: When pressure arises, people use even the dhamma to get rid of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not to endure it and understand it through enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why they're not enduring it rightly, and that's why that's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why that's management versus uprooting.